So good to see you. Good to see you, too.
만나 뵙게 되어 정말 반갑습니다. 저도 반갑습니다.
It was in San Francisco. Yes, I know.
샌프란시스코에서였죠. 네, 알고 있습니다.
You are all over the place. I'm curious if this year feels different
여기저기 많이 다니시는데요. 올해가 다르게 느껴지는지 궁금합니다.
than the last time you were in Davos. Gemini three is out.
지난번 다보스에 오셨을 때와 비교해서요. 제미니 3가 출시됐습니다.
We've heard that opening. I called it a code red internally.
그 소식은 들었습니다. 내부적으로는 '코드 레드'라고 불렀습니다.
Do you feel like Google got its mojo back?
구글이 다시 활력을 되찾았다고 느끼십니까?
Well, I'm not sure if that's for me to say, but I feel like we had a very good
글쎄요, 제가 그렇게 말할 처지는 아니지만, 우리는 매우 좋은
year. So it's been hard work, really hard work
한 해를 보냈다고 느낍니다. 그래서 정말 많은 노력과 고된 작업이 필요했습니다.
getting our technology and the models sort of to back to state of the art.
우리의 기술과 모델을 다시 최첨단 수준으로 되돌리는 일이었죠.
I think we did that with Gemini three especially and nanobots on our imaging
특히 제미니 3와 이미징 소프트웨어의 나노봇으로 그 일을 해냈다고 생각합니다.
software. And then I think we've also sort of
그리고 또, 매우 빠르게 출시하는 이 새로운 세상에
adapted really to this new world of shipping very fast.
정말 잘 적응했다고 생각합니다.
Kind of bringing a kind of startup energy to what we do.
우리가 하는 일에 일종의 스타트업 에너지를 불어넣은 셈입니다.
Do you think people underestimated Google or got something wrong?
사람들이 구글을 과소평가했거나 무엇인가를 잘못 이해했다고 보십니까?
Yes, maybe. I'm not sure.
네, 어쩌면요. 확신은 없습니다.
I mean, I think we always had the ingredients, you know, to to to be at
우리는 항상 최전선에 서기 위한 기반과 자원을 갖추고 있었다고 생각합니다.
the forefront of this. Obviously, we've got the long history in
당연히 이 분야에서 오랜 역사를 갖고 있습니다.
it. I think, you know, over the last decade,
그리고 지난 10년을 돌아보면,
Google and DeepMind, between us, we've invented most of the breakthroughs that
구글과 딥마인드는 함께 현대 AI 산업이 의존하는
the modern A.I. industry relies on.
대부분의 혁신을 만들어냈습니다.
Now see Transformers, most famously by AlphaGo Deep reinforcement learning
트랜스포머, 가장 유명한 알파고, 심층 강화학습 같은 것들이요.
these things. And we have these incredible product
그리고 우리는 놀라운 제품군과
surfaces billions user services. The natural fit for A.I.
수십억 사용자 기반의 서비스 접점을 갖고 있습니다. AI가 자연스럽게 스며들 곳은
actually from search to email to to to chrome and but it's just getting all of
검색부터 이메일, 크롬까지 다양하지만, 결국 중요한 것은
that together and organized in the right way.
그 모든 것을 한데 모아 올바른 방식으로 정리하는 일이었습니다.
And I think we've done that in the last couple of years, and there's still a lot
그리고 지난 몇 년 동안 그 일을 해냈다고 생각합니다만
more work to do, but I think we're starting to see the fruits of that.
아직도 할 일이 많습니다. 그래도 그 결실이 나타나기 시작했다고 봅니다.
If you think you have an advantage, how big do you think your advantage is?
우리가 우위가 있다고 보신다면, 그 우위가 얼마나 크다고 생각하십니까?
How long does it last? Well, I think everything starts with
그 우위는 얼마나 지속됩니까? 저는 모든 것이
research, in my opinion. And, you know, the models, especially
연구에서 시작한다고 생각합니다. 그리고 특히 모델은
being at the state of the art on all the different benchmarks.
다양한 벤치마크에서 최첨단 수준에 있어야 합니다.
And that's what we focused on first when we put Google and DeepMind together.
구글과 딥마인드를 통합했을 때 우리가 가장 먼저 집중한 것도 그것이었습니다.
And I think with the Gemini series, you're very happy with how that's going.
그리고 제미니 시리즈의 진행 상황에는 매우 만족하고 있습니다.
There's a lot more work to do there. But I think we're the only organization
그 부분에도 할 일이 더 많습니다. 하지만 우리는 유일하게
that has the full stack from the TTPs and the and the hardware, the data
TPU부터 하드웨어, 데이터
centers, the cloud business, the Frontier lab, and all of these amazing
센터, 클라우드 비즈니스, 프런티어 랩, 그리고 이 모든 놀라운
products that can, you know, kind of natural fits for A.I..
제품까지 전체 스택을 가진 조직은 우리뿐이라고 생각합니다. 모두 AI에 자연스럽게 맞습니다.
So really, structurally from first principles, we should be doing very
그래서 구조적으로, 근본 원칙부터 보자면 우리는 매우
well. And I think there's actually a lot more
잘할 수 있어야 합니다. 그리고 사실 아직 더 많은
headroom to come from here. I wonder what a day in the life of a
성장 여력이 남아 있다고 봅니다.
frontier model leading ACO is like. Like I've read that you do most of your
프런티어 모델을 이끄는 CEO의 하루는 어떤지 궁금합니다. 새벽 1시에서 4시 사이에
thinking between one and four. AM Yes, that's right.
주로 생각을 정리하신다고 들었습니다. 네, 맞습니다.
Is it ever not a code red inside? Like, do you ever feel comfortable?
내부에서 코드 레드가 아닌 때가 있나요? 편안하다고 느끼신 적이 있나요?
No. You never feel comfortable.
아니요. 결코 편안하다고 느끼지 않습니다.
I mean, we try, you know, code red zone for very special circumstances.
물론 노력은 합니다만, '코드 레드'는 아주 특별한 상황에만 쓰려고 합니다.
But it's always I mean, for the last I would say three, four years, it's been
하지만 늘 그렇습니다. 지난 3~4년 동안은
unbelievably intense. And, you know, 100 hour weeks,
믿을 수 없을 만큼 강도 높았습니다. 주 100시간 근무에,
50, you know, 50 weeks a year. And that's the norm.
1년에 50주를 그렇게 합니다. 그게 정상입니다.
And I think that's what you have to do at the forefront of this unbelievably
그리고 이렇게 믿을 수 없을 만큼 빠르게 움직이는 기술의 최전선에서는
fast moving technology. It's ferociously competitive out there.
그렇게 할 수밖에 없습니다. 경쟁이 극도로 치열합니다.
Maybe the most intense competition has ever been in technology.
기술 분야 역사상 가장 치열한 경쟁일지도 모릅니다.
And the stakes are incredibly high. AGI and, you know, all of that, that
그리고 판돈이 믿을 수 없을 만큼 큽니다. AGI 같은 것들까지,
that can mean so commercially, scientifically.
그것이 상업적으로도 과학적으로도 갖는 의미가 엄청나기 때문입니다.
And then if you add all the excitement of what we're doing and, you know, using
게다가 우리가 하는 일 자체의 흥분에 더해,
it as my passion, as you know, is exploring scientific, you know, problems
아시다시피 제 열정은 AI로 과학적 문제를 탐구하고
with AI, accelerating scientific discovery itself.
과학적 발견 자체를 가속하는 것입니다.
This is what I've always dreamed about and I've worked my whole life on A.I.
이것이 제가 늘 꿈꿔 왔던 일이고, 저는 평생 AI에 매달려
towards this moment. So it's sort of hard to sleep because
이 순간을 향해 왔습니다. 그래서 잠을 자기 어렵습니다. 왜냐하면
there's so much work to do. But also, it's it's it's there's so much
할 일이 너무 많기 때문입니다. 하지만 동시에, 정말로
exciting things to to look into and to to push forward.
살펴보고 더 밀어붙일 흥미로운 것들이 너무 많습니다.
I mean, I know you're very focused on driving scientific progress, just
그러니까 과학적 진보를 이끄는 데 매우 집중하고 계시다는 건 압니다만,
discovering new materials. Even we've seen now Gemini being
새로운 소재를 발견하는 것뿐 아니라, 이제 제미니가
integrated into humanoid robots. Is the alpha fold moment for the
휴머노이드 로봇에 통합되는 것도 봤습니다. 물리 세계에서의
physical world and I here. What is that and what does that look
물리 세계에서의 AI는 무엇이며, 그것은 어떤 모습입니까?
like? Yeah, I spent a lot of the last year
그렇습니까? 네, 저는 지난 1년 동안 많은 시간을
actually looking very carefully into robotics.
실제로 로보틱스를 매우 면밀히 들여다보는 데 썼습니다.
I do think we're on the cusp of a kind of breakthrough moment in physical
저는 우리가 물리적 지능에서 일종의 돌파구가 열릴 문턱에 와 있다고 생각합니다.
intelligence. I still think we're about 18 months, two
물리적 지능 분야에서요. 다만 저는 아직 대략 18개월에서 2년 정도는
years away from doing. We need to do more research.
더 시간이 필요하다고 봅니다. 더 많은 연구가 필요합니다.
But I think the foundation models like
하지만 저는 이런 기반 모델들이
Gemini show the way forward. I mean, from the beginning we made
예를 들어 Gemini 같은 기반 모델이 앞으로의 길을 보여 준다고 생각합니다. 처음부터 저희는
Gemini multimodal so you could understand the physical world for
Gemini를 멀티모달로 만들어 물리 세계를 이해할 수 있게 했습니다.
multiple reasons. One was so we could build a universal
그 이유는 여러 가지였고, 그중 하나는 범용
assistant. Maybe that exists on your glasses or
어시스턴트를 만들기 위해서였습니다. 안경에 있거나
your phone that understands the world around you.
휴대폰에 탑재되어 주변 세계를 이해하는 형태일 수도 있습니다.
But of course, a second use of that would be for robotics.
하지만 물론 두 번째 용도는 로보틱스였습니다.
So what is this, that moment for the physical world look like?
그렇다면 물리 세계에서의 그 순간은 어떤 모습입니까?
I think it's it's having robots, you know, reliably do useful tasks out in
제 생각에는 로봇이 실제 세계에서 유용한 작업을
the world. And I think there's a few things holding
신뢰성 있게 수행하는 것입니다. 그리고 이를 가로막는 요인이 몇 가지 있습니다.
that back. Still.
여전히 그것을 가로막고 있습니다.
Part of it is the algorithms are still not quite there.
그중 일부는 알고리즘이 아직 충분히 성숙하지 않았다는 점입니다.
They need a little bit more robustness. They have to work with less data than
조금 더 견고해야 하고, 연구실에서 얻는 것보다 더 적은 데이터로도
you get for the labs or the models that work on just digital.
순수 디지털 모델에서처럼 충분한 데이터를 얻지 못한 상태에서 작동해야 합니다.
Well, you can sort of create synthetic data a lot harder to make that kind of
물론 합성 데이터를 어느 정도 만들 수는 있지만, 그런 종류의
data. And there's still sort of some problems
데이터를 만드는 것은 훨씬 더 어렵습니다. 그리고 여전히 몇 가지 문제가 있습니다.
in the hardware that are not solved specifically things like the arm and the
하드웨어 측면에서도 아직 해결되지 않은 문제들이 있는데, 특히 팔과
hand. Actually, when you look into robotics
손 같은 부분입니다. 사실 로봇공학을
very carefully, you get a newfound appreciation, at least I did, for the
아주 자세히 들여다보면, 적어도 저는
human hand, and how exquisite evolution is design that it's incredible and it's
인간의 손에 대해 새삼 감탄하게 되었고, 진화의 설계가 얼마나 정교한지 정말 놀랍습니다. 그리고
very hard to match the reliability, the strength and the dexterity that the
인간의 손이 가진 신뢰성, 힘, 그리고 정교함과 민첩성을
human hand has. So there's still quite a lot, I, in my
맞먹게 구현하기가 매우 어렵습니다. 그래서 제 생각에는 아직도
opinion, pieces that put together. But there's very exciting things.
맞춰야 할 조각이 꽤 많습니다. 하지만 매우 흥미로운 일들도 있습니다.
I mean, we just announced a new deep collaboration with the Boston Dynamics.
예를 들어, 저희는 방금 보스턴 다이내믹스와의 새로운 심층 협력을 발표했습니다.
They've got some very exciting robots and end die and actually applying it to
그들은 매우 흥미로운 로봇을 보유하고 있고, 실제로 이를
automotive manufacturing. And we'll see over the next year how
자동차 제조에 적용하고 있습니다. 그리고 앞으로 1년 동안
that goes in sort of prototype form. And then maybe in a year or two we'll
프로토타입 형태로 그것이 어떻게 진행되는지 보게 될 것이고, 그리고 1~2년 뒤에는
have some really impressive demonstrations that we can scale up.
확대 적용할 수 있는 정말 인상적인 시연을 보여줄 수도 있습니다.
A year ago, deep sea seemed cataclysmic for the West.
1년 전에는 딥시크가 서방에 재앙처럼 보였습니다.
Now, a year later, it's it's quiet. China seems to have been quieter.
그런데 1년이 지난 지금은 조용합니다. 중국도 더 조용해 보입니다.
Yes. Has your opinion on competition from
네. 중국과의 경쟁에 대한
China changed? Not really.
의견이 바뀌었나요? 꼭 그렇지는 않습니다.
I mean, I didn't think it was cataclysmic in the first place.
애초에 저는 그것이 재앙적이라고 생각하지 않았습니다.
I think it was a massive overreaction in the West.
서방의 반응이 과도했다고 봅니다.
It was impressive. And I think it shows that the Chinese
인상적이긴 했습니다. 그리고 그것은 중국이
are very capable that the leading companies I think companies like
매우 유능하다는 것을 보여줬고, 선도 기업들, 이를테면
Bytedance actually, I would say are the most capable and they're maybe only six
바이트댄스 같은 회사들이 가장 역량이 뛰어나다고 말할 수 있으며, 아마도 겨우 6개월
months behind, not one or two years behind the frontier.
정도 뒤처져 있을 뿐, 최전선에서 1~2년 뒤처진 것은 아닙니다.
So I think that's what they showed. Some of the claims were overexaggerated
그래서 저는 그들이 그런 점을 보여줬다고 생각합니다. 다만 일부 주장들은 과장되었습니다.
about, you know, the amount of compute they used and being so minimal and so
예를 들어 사용한 연산 자원이 매우 적었다는 등의
on, because they relied on some Western models and also fine tuning on the
주장 말인데요, 서방의 일부 모델에 의존했고 또
outputs of some of the leading Western models.
서방의 선도 모델들이 낸 출력으로 파인튜닝을 했기 때문입니다.
So it wasn't sort of denied. MALVEAUX And the other thing I think so
그래서 완전히 근거 없는 얘기는 아니었습니다. 말보: 그리고 또 한 가지는
far is not yet to be seen is can China actually the Chinese companies innovate
아직 지켜봐야 하는데, 중국의 기업들이 실제로
beyond the frontier themselves so that that, you know, they're gaining, that
스스로 최전선을 넘어서는 혁신을 할 수 있느냐는 점입니다. 즉
they're very good at kind of catching up to where the frontier is and
그들은 최전선이 있는 지점까지 따라잡는 데는 매우 능하고
increasingly capable of that. But I think they've yet to show they can
그 능력도 점점 커지고 있지만, 저는 그들이
innovate beyond the frontier. You helped define AGI.
최전선을 넘어 혁신할 수 있다는 것을 아직 보여주지 못했다고 봅니다. AGI를 정의하는 데 도움을 주셨습니다.
You have said we have a 50% chance of getting there by 2030.
2030년까지 거기에 도달할 확률이 50%라고 말씀하셨습니다.
Is that still your timeline? It is.
그 일정이 아직도 유효합니까? 네, 그렇습니다.
And is AGI still a useful target for you?
그리고 AGI는 여전히 유용한 목표입니까?
I think so. I think it's a very good list in my
그렇다고 생각합니다. 제
timeline, and it's a little bit longer than some others that your observation
일정에서는 매우 좋은 기준이고, 다른 사람들보다 조금 더 긴 편입니다만, 당신 말씀처럼
is that you're here. But my bar is quite high.
그렇게 보일 수 있습니다. 하지만 제 기준은 꽤 높습니다.
It's it's the it's the ability to, you know, a system that exhibits all the
즉, 인간이 가진 모든
cognitive capabilities humans have. And I think we're still clearly quite
인지 능력을 보여주는 시스템이라는 뜻입니다. 그리고 우리는 아직도 분명히
far from that. That means, you know, things in like
거기서 꽤 멀리 떨어져 있다고 봅니다. 예를 들어
scientific creativity, not just solving a conjecture or solving a problem in
과학적 창의성 같은 것들인데, 단지 어떤 추측을 풀거나 과학의 문제를
science, but actually coming up with the hypothesis or the problem in the first
푸는 것이 아니라, 처음부터 가설이나 문제 자체를
place. And as any scientist knows, finding the
만들어내는 것입니다. 그리고 어떤 과학자든 알듯이, 올바른
right question is actually often way harder than finding the answer.
질문을 찾는 것이 답을 찾는 것보다 실제로는 종종 훨씬 더 어렵습니다.
So I don't you know, it's not clear that that these systems have that capability
그래서 이런 시스템들이 그런 역량을 갖고 있는지는 분명하지 않습니다.
that they definitely don't right now. I think they will eventually, but it's
지금은 분명히 없다고 생각합니다. 언젠가는 갖게 되겠지만,
not clear what's needed still. And as things like continue learning,
아직 무엇이 필요한지는 분명하지 않습니다. 그리고 지속 학습 같은 것들,
you know, online learning, going beyond what they've been sort of trained for,
즉 온라인 학습처럼, 자신들이 훈련받은 범위를 넘어서는 것들이 계속되면
and then they're static out in the world, they need to learn on the fly.
세상에 나가서는 정적인 존재가 되는데, 그때는 즉석에서 학습해야 합니다.
So there's quite a few, in my view, missing capabilities that are quite
그래서 제 관점에서는, 꽤 여러 가지 빠져 있는 역량들이 있고 그것들이 상당히
critical to what I would regard as an AGI system.
제가 AGI 시스템이라고 보려면 매우 중요합니다.
Google's a major investor, and Anthropic Del Rio was here earlier today.
구글은 주요 투자자이고, Anthropic Del Rio가 오늘 앞서 여기 있었습니다.
Do you agree or disagree with his prediction that I will wipe away 50% of
그가 5년 안에 AI가
entry level white collar jobs in five years?
초급 화이트칼라 일자리의 50%를 사라지게 할 것이라는 예측에 동의하십니까, 아니면 반대하십니까?
I think it's that's also my time and my view on that would be a lot longer.
제 생각에는, 제 시간표와 제 관점에서는 그보다 훨씬 더 오래 걸릴 것 같습니다.
I mean, I think we're starting to see maybe the beginnings of that this year
물론 올해 들어 어쩌면 그 시작을 보고 있는 것 같기도 합니다,
in terms of maybe entry level jobs or internships, those types of things.
초급 일자리나 인턴십 같은 것들에서 말입니다.
But I think there's we would have to solve a lot more of this consistency
하지만 저는, 이런 일관성 문제를 훨씬 더 많이 해결해야 한다고 생각합니다,
that doesn't have Right. And I call it jacket intelligence, as
현재는 그게 없습니다, 그렇죠. 저는 그것을 재킷 지능이라고 부르는데,
we're very good at certain things and it's very poor.
우리는 어떤 것들은 매우 잘하지만 다른 것들은 매우 형편없습니다.
The current systems are other things. And if you want to offload or delegate
현재 시스템들도 마찬가지로 어떤 것들은 그렇습니다. 그리고 오늘날처럼
an entire task to say an agent, rather than having what we have today,
보조 프로그램 같은 것들이 아니라, 예를 들어 에이전트에게 전체 작업을
which are more like assistive programs, you're going to need a lot more
넘기거나 위임하고 싶다면, 전반적으로 훨씬 더 많은 일관성이 필요합니다.
consistency across the board. It's no good for it to be good at 95% of
그 작업의 95%만 잘하는 것은 소용이 없습니다.
that task. You need it to be good at the whole task
전체 작업을 잘해야 합니다.
for you to be able to actually just sort of fire and forget on it.
그래야 실제로 그냥 맡겨두고 잊어버리는 방식으로 사용할 수 있습니다.
So I think this there's there's still quite a lot more to be done before we'll
그래서 제 생각에는, 그런 수준의 혼란을 보게 되기 전까지는
see that kind of disruption. But that kind of disruption will happen.
아직 해야 할 일이 꽤 많이 남아 있습니다.
I think eventually, sure. I mean, in the limit with AGI, you know,
하지만 그런 혼란은 일어날 것입니다.
if you have systems like that, I think that changes the whole economy.
결국에는요, 물론입니다. 한계적으로 AGI가 있다면 말이죠,
But way beyond the question of jobs, I think potentially if we build it right,
그런 시스템이 있다면, 저는 그것이 경제 전체를 바꾼다고 생각합니다.
we we're in a post scarcity world where we solve some of the kind of fundamental
하지만 일자리 문제를 훨씬 넘어, 잠재적으로 우리가 제대로 만든다면
nodes of the world like energy sources, new clean, renewable, basically free
우리는 결핍 이후의 세계에 들어설 수 있고, 에너지원 같은 세계의 근본적인
energy sources. If we solve fusion, something like that,
매듭들을 풀 수 있습니다, 새롭고 깨끗하며 재생 가능하고 사실상 무료인
with the help of A.I. new materials, I think we'll be, you
에너지원 말입니다. 예를 들어 핵융합 같은 것을 해결한다면,
know, five, ten years past. AGI will be in a in a radical abandoned
AI의 도움을 받아 새로운 소재까지 포함해서요, 그러면 우리는
world. And so what does that mean with, you
AGI 이후 5년, 10년쯤 지나면 급진적으로 풍요로운
know, to the economy and and how how society works?
세계에 있을 것이라고 생각합니다. 그렇다면 경제는, 그리고 사회는
Actually, before we get to a post scarcity world, though, if we get there,
사실, 우리가 탈희소성 세계에 도달하기 전에도, 물론 거기까지 간다면요,
there is so much anxiety about what happens in between.
그 사이에 무슨 일이 벌어질지에 대한 불안이 정말 큽니다.
You know, I'm a mom. I know you have kids.
아시다시피 저는 엄마이고, 당신도 아이가 있는 걸로 압니다.
Like what scares you most for them?
아이들에 대해 가장 두려운 점은 무엇인가요?
What do you talk to them about? What do you tell them that's coming?
아이들과는 무엇을 이야기하나요? 앞으로 올 일에 대해 무엇이라고 말해주나요?
I mean, I've just heard so many. Oh, my gosh.
그러니까요, 저는 정말 많은 얘기를 들었어요, 세상에.
For college graduates are going to have such a hard time.
대학 졸업생들이 정말 힘든 시간을 겪게 될 거라는 말이요.
Well, I don't know about that. Look, I think it's it's it's going to be
음, 그건 잘 모르겠습니다만, 보세요, 저는 그게, 그게, 그게 아마
an age of disruption, just like the Industrial revolution was maybe ten acts
산업혁명처럼 격변의 시대가 될 거라고 생각합니다, 아마 그 열 배쯤
of that, which is kind of unbelievable to think about ten times faster than I
일 텐데요, 제가 보통 말하는 것보다 열 배나 더 빠르다고 생각하면 믿기 어려울 정도입니다.
usually describe it. It's going to be ten times bigger and
제가 보통 말하는 것보다요; 규모는 열 배 더 크고
ten times faster. The Industrial Revolution, two years,
속도도 열 배 더 빠를 겁니다. 산업혁명은 2년,
100 now get. So 100 X of it.
100년이 걸렸다고 하면요, 그러면 100배인 셈입니다.
No, I say this to everyone, but I think that comes with it.
아니요, 저는 이 얘길 누구에게나 하지만, 그와 함께
Huge opportunities. And I also am just a big believer in
엄청난 기회가 따라온다고 봅니다. 그리고 저는
human ingenuity. We're extremely adaptable because our
인간의 창의성과 기발함을 크게 믿습니다. 우리는
minds are so general. You know, the human mind is very
마음이 매우 범용적이기 때문에 아주 적응력이 큽니다. 인간의 마음은
general. We've adapt to look at the modern world
정말 범용적이죠. 우리는 적응해왔고, 현대 세계를
around us. We, you know, our hunter gatherer minds
우리 주변에 만들어냈습니다. 아시다시피 우리의 수렵채집인 뇌가
have managed to build modern civilization.
현대 문명을 만들어내는 데 성공했습니다.
So I think we'll adapt again. I think it's a little bit unprecedented
그래서 저는 우리가 또다시 적응할 거라고 봅니다. 다만 이건 다소 전례가 없습니다,
because of the speed of it. Usually it takes one generation or two
속도 때문이죠. 보통은 이런 변화가 일어나려면 한 세대나 두 세대가
generations for a transformation like this to happen and the magnitude of the
걸리고, 이런 변혁의 규모도
transformative power of this technology. But I think the kids today, you know,
이 기술의 변혁적 힘이 엄청납니다. 하지만 저는 오늘날 아이들이,
I'd be encouraging them to get incredibly proficient with these new
이 새로운 도구들을 놀라울 정도로 능숙하게 다루도록
tools and native with them, and they're almost equivalent of giving them
자연스럽게 익히도록 격려하겠습니다, 그건 거의 아이들에게
superpowers, you know, in the creative arts that you could probably do the job
초능력을 주는 것과 비슷합니다. 창작 예술 분야에서라면 아마
of, you know, what would have taken ten people in one.
원래 열 사람이 하던 일을 한 사람이 해낼 수도 있습니다.
And I think that means, you know, if you entrepreneurial, if you're creative with
그리고 이는, 그러니까, 여러분이 기업가 정신이 있고, 창의적으로
game design films, projects, you can probably get a lot more done and break
게임 디자인이나 영화 같은 프로젝트를 한다면, 훨씬 더 많은 일을 해내고
into. Those industries a lot more easily than
그 산업들에 진입하는 것도
you could in the past, as you know. A new upcoming talent.
과거보다 훨씬 더 쉬울 겁니다, 아시다시피요. 떠오르는 새로운 인재가요.
Some folks have advocated for a pause to give regulation time to catch up, to
일부 사람들은 규제가 따라잡을 시간을 주고
give society time to sort of adjust to some of these changes.
사회가 이런 변화에 어느 정도 적응할 시간을 주기 위해 일시 중단을 주장해왔습니다.
In a perfect world, you knew that every other company would pause.
이상적인 세상이라면, 다른 모든 회사가 멈출 거라고 확신할 수 있겠죠.
If every country would pause. Would you advocate for that?
모든 나라가 잠시 멈춘다면요. 그렇게 하자고 주장하시겠습니까?
I think so. I mean, I've been on record saying what
그렇다고 생각합니다. 저는 공개적으로 제가 무엇을 바라는지 말해 왔고,
I'd like to see happen. It was always my dream of the kind of
어떤 일이 일어나길 바라는지요. 그것은 늘 제 꿈이었고,
the road map at least I had when I started out the mind 15 years ago and
제가 15년 전 딥마인드를 시작했을 때 마음속에 그려 둔 로드맵이자,
start working in, you know, 25 years ago now, was that as we got close to this
사실 지금으로부터 25년 전쯤 이 일을 시작했을 때의 생각은, 우리가 이 순간에 가까워질수록
moment, this threshold moment of AGI arriving,
AGI가 도래하는 이 문턱의 순간, 이 임계의 순간에 가까워질수록요,
we would maybe collaborate, you know, in a scientific way.
우리가 과학적인 방식으로 서로 협력할 수도 있을 것이라고요.
I sometimes talk about setting up an international CERN equivalent for AI
저는 때때로 AI를 위한 국제적 CERN에 해당하는 기관을 세우자고 이야기합니다.
where all the best minds in the world would collaborate together and do the
그곳에서 전 세계 최고의 인재들이 함께 협력해 함께 연구를 진행하는 것이지요.
final steps in a very rigorous scientific way involving all of society,
사회 전체가 참여하는 매우 엄격한 과학적 방식으로 마지막 단계를 밟고,
maybe philosophers and social scientists and economists, as well as technologists
기술자들뿐 아니라 철학자, 사회과학자, 경제학자 같은 분들도 참여하는 것입니다.
to kind of figure out what we want from this technology and how to utilize it in
이 기술에서 우리가 무엇을 원하는지, 그리고 이를 어떻게 활용할지 알아보기 위해서요.
a in a in a way that benefits all of humanity.
인류 전체에 이익이 되도록 말입니다.
And I think that's what's at stake. Unfortunately, it kind of needs
그리고 저는 그것이 바로 걸린 문제라고 생각합니다. 하지만 안타깝게도 이는
international collaboration, though, because even if one company or even one
국제적 협력이 필요합니다. 왜냐하면 한 회사나 심지어 한
nation or even the West decided to do that, it's the has no use unless the
국가, 혹은 서방만 그렇게 하기로 결정하더라도, 전 세계가 동의하지 않으면
whole world agrees, at least on some kind of minimum standards.
최소한 어떤 최저 기준에라도 합의하지 않으면 의미가 없기 때문입니다.
And, you know, international cooperation is a little bit tricky at the moment.
그리고 아시다시피 지금은 국제 협력이 다소 까다로운 상황입니다.
So that's going to have to change if we want to, to to have that kind of
그래서 우리가 AGI로 가는 마지막 단계에서 그런 종류의
rigorous scientific approach to the final steps to AGI.
엄격한 과학적 접근을 하려면, 그 상황이 바뀌어야 합니다.
So if AGI comes in, let's say 2030, we don't have the regulations set up yet.
그렇다면 AGI가 예를 들어 2030년에 온다고 했을 때, 아직 규제가 갖춰져 있지 않다면
Are we destined for something difficult? Well, then where you know, I doesn't I
우리는 어려운 상황을 맞게 되는 건가요? 음, 그러면, 아시다시피, 저는, 저는
think I'm still optimistic that enough of the leading players will
저는 여전히 주요 주체들 가운데 충분히 많은 이들이
kind of communicate together and hopefully collaborate at least on things
서로 소통하고, 바라건대 적어도 몇 가지에서는 협력하리라고 낙관합니다.
like safety and security protocols. There's a lot of that already.
안전과 보안 프로토콜 같은 것들에서는요. 그런 일은 이미 많이 하고 있습니다.
We work quite closely with Anthropic, for example, on those things, and that
예를 들어 저희는 그런 것들에 대해 Anthropic과도 꽤 긴밀히 협력하고 있고,
would be needed then, you know, maybe kind of more peer based cooperation if
그런 협력은 필요할 것입니다. 그리고 국제적인 틀이 작동하지 않는다면, 아시다시피, 아마
we can't get that international thing to work.
동료들 간 협력 같은, 보다 피어 기반의 협력이 필요할 수도 있습니다.
But I would, you know, that would be a lot more like Sam to cooperate with you.
하지만 저는, 아시다시피, 그러면 여러분과 샘이 협력하는 것에 더 가까운 모습일 겁니다.
I potentially I'm you know, I think I'm on pretty good terms with pretty much
저는 아시다시피, 대체로는
all the other leaders of all the leading labs.
주요 연구소의 다른 리더들 대부분과 꽤 좋은 관계를 유지하고 있다고 생각합니다.
I mean, I think if the stakes are high enough and I think a lot of it is
그러니까 이해관계가 충분히 크다면, 그리고 그중 많은 부분은
understanding what's at stake and what the risks are.
무엇이 걸려 있는지와 위험이 무엇인지 이해하는 것이라고 생각합니다.
And I think that will become clearer to everyone in the next two or three years.
그리고 그 점은 앞으로 2~3년 안에 모두에게 더 분명해질 것이라고 생각합니다.
So let's talk about the technology and the next curve.
그럼 기술과 다음 곡선에 대해 이야기해 보겠습니다.
Yang Coombs has said he doesn't think Transformers and lamps alone will get us
얀 르쿤은 트랜스포머와 LLM만으로는 우리를
to AGI. Do you agree or disagree?
AGI로 데려가지 못한다고 말했습니다. 동의하십니까, 아니면 반대하십니까?
And and, you know, if they're dead ends and what are we doing?
그리고, 아시다시피, 그것들이 막다른 길이라면 우리는 무엇을 하고 있나요?
Yes. No, I disagree that they're dead ends.
네, 아니요, 저는 그것들이 막다른 길이라는 데에는 동의하지 않습니다.
But obviously, I think that's clearly wrong.
하지만 저는 그건 분명히 틀렸다고 생각합니다.
I mean, they're so amazingly useful already.
그러니까 이미 정말 놀라울 정도로 유용합니다.
But I think the way I say is an empirical question.
다만 제가 말하고 싶은 것은, 이것이 경험적 질문이라는 겁니다.
I think it's a scientific question whether they're going to be enough on
그것이 충분한지 여부는 과학적 질문입니다.
their own. I think it's a 5050 that, you know, just
그것들만으로요. 저는, 아시다시피, 그 가능성이 반반이라고 봅니다, 즉
scaling up existing methods with some tweaks will be enough.
약간의 조정을 더해 기존 방법을 계속 스케일업하는 것만으로도 충분할지요.
It might be. And you have to do that.
그럴 수도 있습니다. 그리고 그렇게 해봐야 합니다.
And I think that's useful work because at a minimum, the way I look at it is
그리고 제 생각엔 그건 유용한 작업인데, 최소한 제가 보기에는
these lambs will be a component, a massively important component of the
이런 LLM들은 최종 시스템의 한 구성 요소가 될 텐데, 매우 중요한 구성 요소입니다.
final system. The only question in my mind is, is it
제 머릿속에서 유일한 질문은, 그것이
is it the only component? Right.
유일한 구성 요소인가 하는 점입니다. 맞습니다.
And I could imagine there are one or two breakthroughs, maybe a small handful,
그리고 저는 한두 번의 돌파구, 어쩌면 소수의 돌파구가 있을 수 있다고 상상할 수 있고,
you know, less than five that still need it from here, right?
그러니까 다섯 개도 안 되는 것들이 여기서부터 아직 필요하다고요, 그렇지요?
Yes. And so, you know, and those might be
네. 그래서, 아시다시피, 그런 것들은
things like world models. That's something I've talked about we're
세계 모델 같은 것일 수 있습니다. 제가 말해 왔고 우리가 작업하고 있는 분야입니다.
working on. In fact, we have the best world model
사실 우리는 현재 최고의 세계 모델을 갖고 있는데,
currently, which is GENI, our GENI system.
그것이 GENIE, 저희 GENIE 시스템입니다.
And I work on that directly and I think it's very important.
그리고 저는 그걸 직접 연구하고 있고, 매우 중요하다고 생각합니다.
But also things like continue learning and having consistent systems that are,
하지만 지속 학습 같은 것과, 일관된 시스템을 갖추는 것도 중요합니다, 즉
you know, don't have these jagged edges that they're good at and not good at.
잘하는 것과 못하는 것이 이런 들쭉날쭉한 모서리로 남아 있지 않도록요.
That's a general system. Shouldn't have that.
일반적인 시스템이라면 그런 것은 있어서는 안 됩니다.
So I think, you know, better reasoning, more long term planning, there's quite a
그래서 더 나은 추론, 더 장기적인 계획 수립 등, 아직 빠진 역량이 꽤 있습니다.
few capabilities that are still missing. And it's an open question whether a new
그리고 새로운 아키텍처나 새로운 돌파구가 필요한지, 아니면
architecture or new breakthrough is needed or more of the same.
같은 것을 더 하는 것으로 되는지는 미지수입니다.
And we're just, from my point of view, from Google, Deepmind's point of view,
그리고 제 관점에서는, 구글과 딥마인드의 관점에서는,
we're pushing as hard as possible. And both those things, both inventing
우리는 가능한 한 강하게 밀어붙이고 있습니다. 그리고 그 두 가지 모두, 즉 발명도 하고
new things and scaling up existing things, so slightly different but
새로운 것을 만들고 기존 것을 확장하는 일 모두를 하고 있습니다. 그래서 약간 다르지만
related. Elias Escovedo said the era of scaling
서로 연관된 일입니다. 엘리아스 에스코베도는 규모 확장의 시대, 즉
and making bigger models make improvements is is nearly over.
더 큰 모델을 만들어 개선을 얻는 시대가 거의 끝났다고 말했습니다.
Is that something you agree? I don't agree.
이에 동의하십니까? 저는 동의하지 않습니다.
I think that his exact quote was this We're back to the age of research.
제 기억에 그의 정확한 말은 이랬습니다. "우리는 연구의 시대로 돌아왔다."
But but and you know, I love Ellie and we're very good friends and we agree on
하지만 저는 엘리를 좋아하고 우리는 매우 친한 친구이며 많은 것에 동의합니다. 그러나 제 견해는
a lot of things. But my view is we never left the age of
우리는 연구의 시대를 떠난 적이 없다는 것입니다.
research, at least from the point of view of the point.
적어도 제 관점에서는 그렇습니다.
We've always invested. We've in my view, we've always had the
우리는 항상 투자해 왔습니다. 제 생각에는 우리는 항상
the deepest and broadest bench, actually Google and DeepMind together we have.
가장 깊고 가장 넓은 인재층을 갖추고 있었습니다. 사실 구글과 딥마인드를 합치면,
The last decade, we've invented about 90% of the breakthroughs that, you know,
지난 10년 동안 현대 산업이 의존하는 돌파구의 약 90%를 발명했습니다.
the modern industry relies on. Of course, Transformers, most famously,
물론 트랜스포머가 가장 유명하지만,
but also, you know, deep reinforcement learning.
심층 강화학습도 있습니다.
AlphaGo these kinds of reinforcement learning techniques.
알파고 같은 강화학습 기법들입니다.
We pioneered all of that. So if some new breakthroughs are
우리가 그 모든 것을 개척했습니다. 그래서 미래에 새로운 돌파구가
required in the future, I would back us to be the ones just like in the past, to
필요해진다면, 저는 과거처럼 앞으로도 우리가
be the ones to make those breakthroughs, you know, in the future.
그 돌파구를 만들어낼 주체가 우리가 될 것이라고 믿습니다, 앞으로도 말입니다.
Last, agree or disagree, Elon says we have entered the singularity.
마지막으로, 동의하십니까 아니면 동의하지 않으십니까? 일론은 우리가 특이점에 들어섰다고 말합니다.
No, I think that's very premature. You know, I think the singularity is
아니요, 저는 그것이 매우 성급하다고 생각합니다. 저는 특이점은
another word for, you know, a full AGI arriving.
완전한 AGI의 도래를 뜻하는 또 다른 말이라고 생각합니다.
And I think I explained earlier why I think that we're still, you know,
그리고 제가 앞서 설명했듯이, 우리는 아직, 그러니까,
nowhere near that. I think we will get there.
그것과는 전혀 거리가 멉니다. 하지만 저는 우리가 거기에 도달할 것이라고 생각합니다.
And, you know, five years, even five years is not a long amount of time if
그리고 5년, 5년조차도
you think about what that is. But I think there's still a lot of work
그것이 무엇을 의미하는지 생각해 보면 긴 시간이 아닙니다. 하지만 그전에 여전히 해야 할 일이 많다고 생각합니다.
to be done before we have anything that looks like the singularity.
특이점처럼 보이는 어떤 것이라도 갖기 전까지는 말입니다.
So talk to us a little bit about the culture inside Google right now to, you
그렇다면 지금 구글 내부의 문화에 대해 조금 말씀해 주십시오, 그러니까,
know, win this race, but do it right. You know the leadership.
이 경쟁에서 이기되 제대로 해내기 위해서요. 리더십과 관련해서도요.
How involved are Larry and Sergey right now?
현재 래리와 세르게이는 얼마나 관여하고 있습니까?
How often do you talk to them and what are their priorities?
그들과 얼마나 자주 이야기하시고, 그들의 우선순위는 무엇입니까?
Yeah, they're very involved in. And, you know, Larry, more on the
네, 두 분 다 매우 깊이 관여하고 계십니다. 그리고 래리는 좀 더
strategic side. You know, I see him at board meetings
전략적인 쪽에 더 집중하십니다. 이사회 회의에서 뵙기도 하고,
and other times when I visit the valley. So, again, it's more hands on on the you
제가 실리콘밸리에 방문할 때 다른 자리에서도 뵙습니다. 그래서 다시 말해, 더 직접적으로 참여하십니다.
know, he's involved in the coding of, you know, on the Gemini team
그러니까 제미니 팀과 관련해 코딩에도 관여하시고
specifically more in the in the in the algorithmic details.
특히 알고리즘 세부 사항, 즉 알고리즘적 디테일에 더 집중하십니다.
And it's great having them both energized around where we are and who
그리고 두 분 모두 우리가 있는 위치에 대해 열정을 갖고 계신 것이 정말 좋습니다. 그리고
wouldn't be, you know, this moment Absolutely incredible moment for
누가 그렇지 않겠습니까, 지금 이 순간은 정말 믿기 어려울 정도로 놀라운 순간입니다.
computer science. So just from a scientific point of view,
컴퓨터 과학에 있어서요. 그래서 순수하게 과학적 관점에서만 보더라도,
which both of them are, it's an incredibly exciting moment in history,
두 분 다 그런 분들이지만, 이는 역사상 믿기 어려울 만큼 흥미로운 순간입니다.
human history, really. And so, of course, everyone wants to be
정말로 인류 역사에서도 그렇습니다. 그래서 물론 모두가
hands on and heavily involved in that. So that's great.
직접 손을 대고 깊이 관여하고 싶어 합니다. 그래서 그 점이 좋습니다.
And and for us, just as as a as an entity, you know, I'm trying to combine
그리고 우리로서는, 하나의 조직으로서, 저는
the best of many worlds. So, you know, startup energy of shipping
여러 세계의 장점을 결합하려고 합니다. 그러니까 스타트업의 에너지, 즉 빠르게 출시하고
things fast and taking risks and doing things like that, which I think you're
위험을 감수하며 일을 추진하는 에너지인데, 여러분께서도
seeing the benefits of, you know, the big company resources is amazing,
그 성과를 보고 계시다고 생각합니다. 그리고 대기업의 자원은 놀랍고
useful, but also protecting the space for long term research still, and
유용하지만, 동시에 장기 연구를 위한 공간도 계속 보호해야 하고,
exploratory research, not just researching what will deliver in, you
탐색적 연구도 마찬가지입니다. 단지
know, three months in a product. I think that would be a mistake, too.
3개월 안에 제품에서 무엇을 내놓을지에만 맞춘 연구만 하는 것은 실수라고 생각합니다.
So I'm trying to balance all of those different factors together.
그래서 저는 이런 여러 요인들을 함께 균형 있게 맞추려고 합니다.
And, you know, I think in the last year things have been going well and I think
그리고 지난 1년 동안은 상황이 잘 흘러가고 있다고 생각하며, 또
we can still do better and I think we still will do better this year.
더 잘할 수도 있고 올해도 더 잘할 것이라고 생각합니다.
But I'm very happy with our trajectory. I think it's the steepest of actually of
하지만 우리의 궤적에는 매우 만족합니다. 실제로 업계에서 그 누구보다도
improvement and progress of anyone in the industry.
개선과 진전의 기울기가 가장 가파르다고 생각합니다.
You are a Nobel laureate and I know how obsessed you are with AI powering
당신은 노벨상 수상자이시며, AI가
scientific research. If I itself, let's say, makes a Nobel
과학 연구를 추진하는 데 얼마나 집요하게 관심을 두고 계신지도 알고 있습니다. 만약 AI 자체가, 예컨대, 노벨상에
worthy discovery, you should get the prize.
걸맞은 발견을 한다면, 상은 당신께서 받으셔야 합니다.
Yeah, I are the human, I think still human, I would say, because I feel like
네, 저는 여전히 인간이 받는 것이 맞다고 말씀드리겠습니다. 왜냐하면
I mean, it depends what you mean by completely on its own right.
완전히 스스로 했다는 것이 무엇을 의미하느냐에 달려 있기 때문입니다.
So for now, these are still tools. And I view them as, you know, like very
그래서 현재로서는 이것들은 여전히 도구입니다. 저는 이것들을, 그러니까
maybe the ultimate scientific tool, but sort of better versions of telescopes
아마도 궁극적인 과학 도구일 수는 있지만, 망원경과
and microscopes. We've always built tools so that we can
현미경의 더 나은 버전 같은 것으로 봅니다. 우리는 항상 도구를 만들어서
investigate the natural world better. We're toolmaking animals, basically.
자연 세계를 더 잘 탐구해 왔습니다. 우리는 기본적으로 도구를 만드는 존재입니다.
That's what distinguishes humans from from the other animals.
그것이 인간을 다른 동물들과 구별해 주는 점입니다.
And that's how superpower and I include computers in that, of course.
그리고 그것이 우리의 초능력이며, 물론 저는 컴퓨터도 그 안에 포함합니다.
And A.I. being the ultimate expression of that.
그리고 AI는 그 궁극적인 표현이라고 할 수 있습니다.
So in some ways, I think of A.I., and I've always thought of it as the
어떤 면에서는 저는 AI를 늘 과학을 하기 위한 궁극의 도구라고 생각해 왔습니다.
ultimate tool to do science. And and I think for the foreseeable
그리고 가까운 미래에도 저는 그렇게 될 것이라고 생각합니다.
future, that's going to be a collaboration with top scientists,
즉 최고의 과학자들과의 협업이 될 것이라고 생각합니다.
putting in the creative ideas and maybe the hypotheses with these amazing tools
과학자들이 창의적인 아이디어와 가설을 이 놀라운 도구들에 입력하며 협업하는 방식입니다.
that enhance, you know, data processing and pattern matching and the exploration
이 도구들은 데이터 처리와 패턴 매칭, 그리고 과학 탐구를 강화해 줍니다.
of science. You you obviously could have sold
이런 도구들 덕분입니다. 그리고 당신은 분명 딥마인드를 누구에게든 매각할 수도 있었을 것입니다.
DeepMind to anyone. And I think all of these companies are
그리고 저는 이런 회사들이 우리에게 많은 신뢰를 요구하고 있다고 생각합니다.
asking a lot of us to trust. Yes.
네.
Especially if regulation doesn't keep up with technology, which history shows it
특히 규제가 기술을 따라가지 못한다면, 역사적으로 보아
probably won't. Why?
아마도 따라가지 못할 가능성이 큽니다. 왜 그렇습니까?
Why should we trust you? And why do you think Google, which I
왜 우리가 당신을 신뢰해야 합니까? 그리고 왜 당신은 구글이
would implicitly think you believe is is the the place that we should believe in
우리가 믿어도 되는 곳이라고 암묵적으로 믿는다고 생각하십니까?
the most? Well, comes to something that feels so
특히 가장 믿어야 할 곳이라고요? 이렇게
risky. Yes.
위험하게 느껴지는 사안에서 말입니다. 네.
I think you need to judge these companies by their actions and also look
저는 이런 회사들은 행동으로 판단해야 하고, 또한
into, you know, the motivations, I would say, of the leaders involved in those
그 일을 이끄는 리더들의 동기 또한 들여다봐야 한다고 생각합니다.
you know, those endeavors. And for me and for us.
그런 시도들에서 말입니다. 그리고 저와 저희에게는
And that's one reason I picked Google as the right home for DeepMind is several
제가 딥마인드의 적절한 터전으로 구글을 선택한 데에는 여러
reasons, the main one being that the founders of Google and the way Google
가지 이유가 있는데, 가장 큰 이유는 구글 창립자들과 구글이
was set up by them was as a scientific company.
그들에 의해 과학 회사로 설립되었다는 점입니다.
You know, many people forget Google itself was a Ph.D.
많은 분들이 잊지만, 구글 자체가 박사 과정
project, right? It was Larry and Sergey project.
프로젝트였습니다. 래리와 세르게이가 시작한 프로젝트였습니다.
So I felt an immediate affinity with with them.
그래서 저는 그들과 즉각적인 친밀감을 느꼈습니다.
And Larry led the acquisition, but also the board who they collected in the
또한 인수는 래리가 주도했지만, 그들이 구성한 이사회도
board. You know, you have John Hennessy's, the
눈여겨볼 만합니다. 예를 들어 존 헤네시 같은 분들이 있고,
chair, who's a Turing Award winner himself, and Francis Arnold, another
의장인 그는 튜링상 수상자이며 프랜시스 아널드 같은 또 다른
Nobel Prize winner. You know, these are unusual people to
노벨상 수상자도 있습니다. 이런 분들은
have on a corporate board. So the whole environment is very
기업 이사회에서는 매우 이례적인 구성입니다. 그래서 전체 환경이
scientific and science. Science and research led and engineering
매우 과학적이며, 과학과 연구가 주도하고 공학이
led as a culture and is deeply ingrained in the culture.
주도하는 문화가 그 조직에 깊이 뿌리내려 있습니다.
And that means doing science at the highest level means being really
이는 최고 수준의 과학을 한다는 것이 곧
rigorous, being thoughtful, and applying the scientific method everywhere you
정말 엄격하고 사려 깊으며, 가능한 모든 곳에 과학적 방법을
can. I think that's not just to the
적용한다는 뜻입니다. 저는 이것이
technology, but it's also to the way you operate as an organization.
기술뿐 아니라 조직 운영 방식에도 해당된다고 생각합니다.
So I feel like, you know, we we're very we tried to be very thoughtful and
그래서 저희는 가능한 한 매우 신중하고
responsible and have as much force as possible over the technologies we put
책임감 있게 행동하며, 세상에 내놓는 기술들에 대해 가능한 한
out in the world. Doesn't mean we'll get everything right
큰 통제력을 가지려 노력해 왔다고 생각합니다. 그렇다고 해서
because it's so complex and so new and nascent and so transformative, this
모든 것을 항상 옳게 해낼 수 있다는 뜻은 아닙니다. 이 기술은
technology. But we hope to coast correct as quickly
너무 복잡하고 새로우며 초기 단계이고, 매우 변혁적이기 때문입니다. 하지만
as possible if there, you know, something does go wrong.
무언가가 잘못된다면 가능한 한 빨리 방향을 바로잡고자 합니다.
And then the final thing I would say is just the I was just attracted by the the
그리고 마지막으로 말씀드리면, 저는 구글이 세상에서 하려는 일들의
types of things Google tries to do in the world.
그런 성격 자체에 끌렸습니다.
You know, organizing the world's information, I think is a very noble
예를 들어 '세상의 정보를 정리한다'는 일은 매우 숭고한
goal, which is obviously Google's mission statement.
목표이며, 이는 분명 구글의 사명 선언문입니다.
And I think it fitted very well with that, with Deepmind's mission statement
그리고 저는 그것이 딥마인드의 사명 선언문과도 매우 잘 맞는다고 생각합니다.
of solving intelligence and using it to to solve everything else.
즉 지능을 해결하고 그것으로 다른 모든 문제를 해결한다는 목표입니다.
And and that was our and I think those two mission statements are natural fit
그리고 저는 이 두 사명 선언문이 자연스럽게 맞물린다고 생각합니다.
AI and organizing the world's information naturally go together.
AI와 세상의 정보를 정리하는 일은 본질적으로 함께 갑니다.
And I think those are the types of products, the types of products that
또 구글은 그런 종류의 제품들로
Google is well known for, for maps to 2 to 2 Gmail to obviously search.
지도, Gmail, 그리고 당연히 검색 같은 것들로 잘 알려져 있습니다.
I think they're genuinely useful products in the world, and I think AI is
저는 그것들이 세상에 정말 유용한 제품들이라고 생각하며, AI는
an easy fit. How that would work with those products
그와 자연스럽게 결합할 수 있다고 봅니다. AI가 그런 제품들과
to enhance them for everybody to use in their everyday lives.
어떻게 결합해 모두가 일상에서 쓰도록 더 향상시킬 수 있을지요.
And I think that's a great thing for the world.
저는 그것이 세상에 매우 좋은 일이라고 생각합니다.
So, you know, I'm happy to be contributing to that.
그래서 그 일에 기여하게 되어 기쁘게 생각합니다.
Okay, so post scarcity world where there people no longer have jobs, what do you
그렇다면 사람들이 더 이상 일자리를 갖지 않는 탈희소성 세계에서, 당신은
personally plan to do with your time once you've achieved all your technical
모든 기술적 목표를 달성한 뒤에 개인적으로 시간을 어떻게 쓰실 계획입니까?
goals? Yes.
목표를 말입니다. 네.
Research is just automating itself, right?
연구는 그냥 스스로 자동화되는 것 아닙니까?
Well, I would love to use it for what I will do.
저는 그것을 제가 할 일에 활용하고 싶습니다.
Post the Singularity is to use it for exploring the limits of physics.
싱귤래리티 이후에는 물리학의 한계를 탐구하는 데 쓰고 싶습니다.
I think that was my my favorite subject at school was the big questions.
학교에서 제가 가장 좋아했던 주제는 '큰 질문'들이었습니다.
You know, what is the fabric of reality? What's the nature of reality?
예를 들면 현실의 구조는 무엇이며, 현실의 본질은 무엇입니까?
What about the nature of consciousness? The answer to the Fermi paradox, all of
의식의 본질은 무엇인지, 페르미 역설의 답은 무엇인지 같은
these things. What is time?
질문들입니다. 시간은 무엇입니까?
What is gravity? I'm amazed more people, you know, we
중력은 무엇입니까? 저는 더 많은 사람들이 이런 것들을
just go around our daily lives, not really thinking about these massive
일상에서 별로 생각하지 않으며 살아간다는 점이 놀랍습니다,
questions that for me are always kind of almost screaming at me for like, what is
저에게는 이런 거대한 질문들이 늘 '답이 무엇이냐'고
the answer to these things, these deep mysteries?
마치 소리치는 것처럼 느껴지기 때문입니다.
And I would like to use AI and to explore all of those things, maybe
그리고 저는 AI를 활용해서 그런 모든 것들을 탐구해 보고 싶습니다, 어쩌면
traveling to the stars as well, with the help of, you know, and new energy
또한, 아시다시피, 새로운 에너지의 도움을 받아 별들로 여행하는 것까지도,
sources and materials and other things that's unlocked by will we all have
에너지원과 재료 같은 것들, 그리고 AI가 열어 주는 다른 것들로 말입니다. 우리가 일을 하지 않으면
meaning and purpose if we don't have work?
우리 모두 의미와 목적을 가질 수 있겠습니까?
Well, I think that's the to be honest with you, that's the thing I worry more
음, 솔직히 말씀드리면 저는 그것이
about than the economics. I think the economics is almost a
경제 문제보다 더 걱정되는 부분이라고 생각합니다. 경제는 거의
political question of like when we get all of these extra benefits and
정치적 질문에 가깝다고 생각합니다. 이런 추가적인 혜택과
productivity, can we make sure that it's shared
생산성을 얻게 될 때, 그것이 공유되도록
for the benefit of everyone? And I think obviously that's what I
모두에게 혜택이 돌아가게 할 수 있겠습니까? 그리고 저는 당연히 그것이
believe in. But then the bigger question, and that
제가 믿는 바입니다. 하지만 더 큰 질문은, 그리고 그것은
is what about purpose and meaning that a lot of us get from our jobs in
우리 중 많은 사람들이 직장에서 얻는 목적과 의미는 어떻게 되느냐는 것입니다,
scientific endeavors? How will we find that in the new world?
과학적 노력에서 말입니다. 우리는 새로운 세계에서 그것을 어떻게 찾겠습니까?
And I think, you know, we will need some new great philosophers, in my opinion,
그리고 제 생각에는, 아시다시피, 새로운 위대한 철학자들이 필요할 것입니다,
to to help with that and thinking that through maybe will, you know, be get
그 문제를 도와주고 그것을 끝까지 생각해 보도록 말입니다. 어쩌면, 아시다시피, 우리는
much more sophisticated with our art and and exploration that we do and things
예술과 탐구 같은 활동도 훨씬 더 세련되게 해 나가게 될 것이고, 그리고
like, you know, extreme sports as many things we do today that aren't just for
아시다시피 극한 스포츠처럼 오늘날 우리가 하는 많은 일들은 단지
economic gain. And perhaps we'll have very esoteric
경제적 이익만을 위한 것은 아닙니다. 그리고 아마도 우리는 매우 난해한
versions of those things in the future. All right.
그런 것들의 미래형 버전도 갖게 될지도 모릅니다. 좋습니다.
So everyone in the room is wondering what they should be doing.
그래서 이 방에 있는 모두가 자신이 무엇을 해야 하는지 궁금해하고 있습니다.
Like, what should I do about what do I do sitting here in Davos in ten years?
예컨대 10년 뒤 다보스에서 여기 앉아 있는 저는 무엇을 해야 합니까?
What is the biggest mistake, do you think people in this room will have made
이 방에 있는 사람들이 가장 크게 저지를 실수는 무엇이라고 생각하십니까
about AI? Well, look, I think there's two things I
AI에 관해서 말입니다. 자, 제 생각에는 두 가지가 있습니다.
would say. One is for the younger generation and
하나는 젊은 세대와
our kids and so on is the only thing we're certain of is there's going to be
우리 아이들 등에게 해당하는데, 우리가 확실히 말할 수 있는 유일한 것은 앞으로
a huge amount of change. So I think in terms of learning skills,
엄청난 변화가 일어날 것이라는 점입니다. 그래서 기술을 배우는 측면에서는,
get ready to because kind of learning to learn is the most important thing.
준비하셔야 합니다. 결국 배우는 법을 배우는 것이 가장 중요합니다.
How can quickly can you adapt to new situations, absorb new information using
새로운 상황에 얼마나 빨리 적응하고, 새로운 정보를 흡수할 수 있느냐가 관건이며
the tools that we have for the CEOs and and business folks in the room?
우리가 가진 도구를 활용하는 것입니다. 이 방의 CEO와 비즈니스 리더들에게는 어떻습니까?
I think the most important thing to do now is there are many providers of
지금 가장 중요한 것은 선도 모델 제공업체가 여러 곳 있다는 점이며,
leading models and leading service providers, and they'll be more for these
선도 서비스 제공업체도 있고, 앞으로 이런 AI 모델의 제공업체는 더 늘 것이라는 점입니다.
A.I. models, you know, pick the partners that
그러니, 아시다시피, 올바른 방식으로 접근하고 있다고
you feel are approaching it in the right way.
여러분이 느끼는 파트너를 선택하십시오.
And so, you know, kind of partner with those that are making the changes and
그리고, 아시다시피, 변화를 만들어 가는 이들과
approaching this technology in the way that you would like to see in the world.
세상에서 그렇게 되기를 바라는 방식으로 이 기술에 접근하는 이들과 협력하십시오.
And I think together we can kind of build that future with, you know, A.I.
그러면 함께, 아시다시피, AI가 다가오면서 우리가 원하는 그 미래를
coming down the line that we will want.
만들어 갈 수 있다고 생각합니다.